<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC3339 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6350 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7095 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7095.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7480 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7480.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7482 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7482.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7483 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7483.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7942 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7942.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC8288 PUBLIC ''
   'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8288.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-loffredo-regext-rdap-jcard-deprecation-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Using JSContact in RDAP">Using JSContact in Registration Data Access Protocol
    (RDAP) JSON Responses</title>
       
    <author fullname="Mario Loffredo" initials="M." surname="Loffredo">
      <organization>IIT-CNR/Registro.it</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Via Moruzzi,1</street>
          <city>Pisa</city>
          <country>IT</country>
          <code>56124</code>
        </postal>
        <email>mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</email>
        <uri>http://www.iit.cnr.it</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Gavin Brown" initials="G" surname="Brown">
      <organization>CentralNic Group plc</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
        <street>Saddlers House, 44 Gutter Lane</street>
        <city>London</city>
        <region>England</region>
        <code>EC2V 6BR</code>
        <country>GB</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+44 20 33 88 0600</phone>
        <email>gavin.brown@centralnic.com</email>
        <uri>https://www.centralnic.com</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>
    <area>Applications and Real-Time</area>
    <workgroup>Registration Protocols Extensions</workgroup>
    <keyword>RDAP</keyword>
    <keyword>jCard</keyword>
    <keyword>JSContact</keyword>
    
    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes how RDAP servers can represent entity contact information in JSON responses using JSContact.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>This document specifies how RDAP servers can use JSContact (<xref target="draft-ietf-jmap-jscontact"/>) to represent the contact information associated with entities in RDAP responses, instead of jCard (<xref target="RFC7095"/>). It also describes the process by which an RDAP server can migrate from jCard to JSContact.</t>

      <section title="Rationale">
        <t>According to the feedback from RDAP Pilot Working Group (<xref target="RDAP-PILOT-WG"/>, a group of RDAP server implementers representing registries and registrars of generic TLDs), the most commonly raised implementation concern, for both servers and clients related to the use of jCard (<xref target="RFC7095"/>) to represent the contact information associated with entities. Working Group members reported jCard to be unintuitive, complicated to implement for both clients and servers, and incompatible with best practices for RESTful APIs.</t>

        <t>JSContact (<xref target="draft-ietf-jmap-jscontact"/>) provides a simpler and more efficient representation for contact information. In addition, it provides a means to represent internationalised and unstructured contact information which cannot currently be represented using jCard. Support for internationalised contact information has been recognised being necessary to facilitate the future internationalisation of registration data directory services.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
      
    <section anchor="JSContact" title="JSContact">
      <t>The JSContact specification defines a data model and JSON representation of contact information that can be used for data storage and exchange in address book or directory applications. It aims to be an alternative to the vCard data format (<xref target="RFC6350"/>) and to be unambiguous, extendable and simple to process. In contrast with jCard, it is not a direct mapping from the vCard data model and expands semantics where appropriate.</t>
      <t>The JSContact specification declares two main object types: &quot;JSCard&quot;, which represents a single contact "card", and &quot;JSCardGroup&quot; which represents a collection of JSCard objects. For the purpose of this document, only JSCard objects are considered.</t>

      <t>JSCard differs from jCard in that it:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>follows an object-oriented rather than array-oriented approach;</t>
        <t>is simple to process;</t>
        <t>requires no extra work in serialization/deserialization from/to a data model;</t>
        <t>includes no "jagged" arrays;</t>
        <t>prefers maps rather than arrays to implement collections;</t>
        <t>is able to represent redacted contacts (both &quot;name&quot; and &quot;fullName&quot; properties are optional).</t>
      </list></t>

      <t><xref target="draft-loffredo-jmap-jscontact-vcard"/> provides informational guidance on the conversion of jCard objects into JSCard objects, and vice versa.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="using-jscontact" title="Using JSCard objects in RDAP Responses">
      <t>Entity objects in RDAP responses MAY include a "jscard" property whose value is a JSCard object instead of the "vCardArray" property defined in RFC 7483.</t>
      <t>Example of an entity object containing a "jscard" property:</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
   {
      "objectClassName" : "entity",
      "handle":"XXXX",
      "jscard":{
        "uid": "XXXX",
        "fullName": { "value": "Joe User" },
        "kind": "individual",
        "preferredContactLanguages": {
          "fr": { "preference": 1 },
          "en": { "preference": 2 }
        },
        "organization": [ { "value": "Example" } ],
        "jobTitle": [ { "value": "Research Scientist" } ],
        "role": [ { "value": "Project Lead" } ],
        "addresses": [
                       {
                         "context": "work",
                         "extension": "Suite 1234",
                         "street": "4321 Rue Somewhere",
                         "locality": "Quebec",
                         "region": "QC",
                         "postcode": "G1V 2M2",
                         "country": "Canada",
                         "coordinates": "geo:46.772673,-71.282945",
                         "timeZone": "Canada/Eastern"
                       },
                       {
                         "context": "private",
                         "fullAddress": {
                           "value": "123 Maple Ave\nSuite 90001\nVancouver\nBC\n1239\n"
                         }
                       }
        ],
        "phones": [
                    { "type": "voice",
                      "context": "work",
                      "isPreferred": true,
                      "value": "tel:+1-555-555-1234;ext=102"
                    }
        ],
        "emails": [
                    {
                      "context": "work",
                      "value": "joe.user@example.com"
                    }
        ],
        "online": [
                    {
                      "context": "work",
                      "type": "uri",
                      "labels": { "key" : true },
                      "value": "http://www.example.com/joe.user/joe.asc"
                    },
                    {
                      "context": "private",
                      "type": "uri",
                      "labels": { "url" : true },
                      "value": "http://example.org"
                    }
        ]
      }
      "roles":[ "registrar" ],
      "publicIds":[
        {
          "type":"IANA Registrar ID",
          "identifier":"1"
        }
      ],
      "remarks":[
        {
          "description":[
            "She sells sea shells down by the sea shore.",
            "Originally written by Terry Sullivan."
          ]
        }
      ],
      "links":[
        {
          "value":"http://example.com/entity/XXXX",
          "rel":"self",
          "href":"http://example.com/entity/XXXX",
          "type" : "application/rdap+json"
        }
      ],
      "events":[
        {
          "eventAction":"registration",
          "eventDate":"1990-12-31T23:59:59Z"
        }
      ],
      "asEventActor":[
        {
          "eventAction":"last changed",
          "eventDate":"1991-12-31T23:59:59Z"
        }
      ]
   }
]]></artwork></figure>

      <section anchor="rdap-conformance" title="RDAP Conformance">
        <t>Servers returning the &quot;jscard&quot; property in their response MUST include &quot;jscard_level_0&quot; in the rdapConformance array.</t>
      </section>

    <section anchor="rdap-query-parameters-specification" title="RDAP Query Parameters Specification">

      <t>Two new query parameters are defined for the purpose of this document.</t>

      <t>The query parameters are OPTIONAL extensions of path segments defined in RFC 7482 <xref target="RFC7482"/>. They are as follows:</t>

      <t><list style="symbols">
        <t>&quot;jscard&quot;: a boolean value that allows a client to obtain the &quot;jscard&quot; property in the RDAP response;<vspace blankLines='1'/></t>
        <t>&quot;jcard&quot;: a boolean value that allows a client to obtain the &quot;vcardArray&quot; property in the RDAP response.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>The use of the above parameters is furtherly explained in section <xref target="transition"/>.</t>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="transition" title="Transition Considerations">

      <section anchor="deprecation-best-practices" title="Best Practices for deprecating a REST API features">
        <t>Deprecation of a REST API feature is a process that should be executed as smartly as possible. Before introducing the basic principles guiding a deprecation process, it could be useful to clarify about the terms deprecation and sunsetting:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>Deprecating an API means it is not usable in its current form for the purpose intended. This usually means that a new version has been created, or the API provider no longer intends to support it.</t>
          <t>Sunsetting is merely a period of time leading up to a deprecation. It is a period of limited support, while deprecation is the period in which support officially ends. In the meantime, the support for an alternate feature replacing the old one might be provided. A sunsetting plan can be set up months or even years in advance of the deprecation announcement.</t>
        </list></t>
        <t>That being said, here are a few guidelines to deprecate a REST API feature:</t>
        <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>"Communicating": REST API providers should announce the intended deprecation communicating the timeline and any other helpful information.</t>
            <t>"Planning a long enough sunset period": a good sunset period is important as it gives API consumers time to work on their clients. Such a period could consist of API updates to fit the future version.</t>
            <t>"Providing alternatives": when entering the sunset period, there may be a provision for elements like redirect URIs, migration endpoints, etc., but, at the same time, the API might still respond to old fashioned requests in order to guarantee backward compatibility for a limited period.</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="rdap-features-supporting-deprecation" title="RDAP Features Supporting a Deprecation Process">
        <t>RDAP enables servers to communicate service information to clients through notices. A notice can include a set of links which can be used to provide clients with references and documentation. For the purpose of this document, two link relation types are used:</t>
        <t><list style="symbols">
          <t>"deprecation" as described in <xref target="draft-dalal-deprecation-header" />;</t>
          <t>"alternate" as described in <xref target="RFC8288" />.</t>
        </list></t>
        <t>The information about the specifications used in the construction of the response is also described by the "rdapConformance" tags.</t>
        <t>Clients are able to ask servers for RDAP features by using appropriate query parameters as described in <xref target="RFC7482" />.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="jcard-deprecation-procedure" title="jCard Deprecation Procedure">
        <t>The procedure for jCard to JSCard migration consists of four contiguous stages, each one corresponding to as many alternatives in providing the contact card. During the procedure, the presence of "jscard_level_0" tag in the rdapConformance array means that JSCard is returned instead of jCard. The time format used in notifying clients about this procedure is defined in <xref target="RFC3339" />.</t>

        <section anchor="jcard-deprecation-procedure-stages" title="Stages">
          <t>Here in the following the four stages are reported in detail:</t>

          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Stage 1 - jCard only provided</t>
            <t>This stage corresponds to providing jCard as default contact card (<xref target="RFC7483" />). The RDAP server is not able to provide an alternate contact card. The rdapConformance array does not contain the "jscard_level_0" tag.<vspace blankLines='1' /></t>

            <t>Stage 2 - jCard sunset</t>
            <t>This stage corresponds to providing jCard as default contact card but the RDAP server is able to alternatively return JSCard if the client sets the query parameter "jscard" to 1/true/yes. The rdapConformance array contains the "jscard_level_0" tag if JSCard is requested.</t>

            <t>The RDAP server is recommended to return a notice titled "jCard sunset end". Such a notice should include a description reporting the jCard sunset end time and two links:

            <list style="symbols">
              <t>"deprecation": a link to a URI-identified resource documenting the jCard deprecation;</t>
              <t>"alternate": if JSCard is not requested, a link to the JSCard version of same resource as identified by the current query string plus the parameter "jscard" set to 1/true/yes (<xref target="stage2-example1" />); otherwise, only the "deprecation" link is provided (<xref target="stage2-example2" />).</t>
            </list></t>
          </list></t>

          <figure anchor="stage2-example1" title="jCard sunset - JSCard not requested"><artwork xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA["notices": [
  {
    "title": "jCard sunset end",
    "description": ["2020-07-01T00:00:00Z"],
    "links": [{
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX",
        "rel": "deprecation",
        "type": "text/html",
        "href": "http://www.example.com/jcard_deprecation.html"
      },
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX",
        "rel": "alternate",
        "type": "application/rdap+json",
        "href": " http://example.net/entity/XXXX?jscard=1"
      }
    ]
  }
]
]]></artwork></figure>
          <figure anchor="stage2-example2" title="jCard sunset - JSCard requested"><artwork xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA["notices": [
  {
    "title": "jCard sunset end",
    "description": ["2020-07-01T00:00:00Z"],
    "links": [
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX?jscard=1",
        "rel": "deprecation",
        "type": "text/html",
        "href": "http://www.example.com/jcard_deprecation.html"
      }
    ]
  }
]
]]></artwork></figure>
          <t><list style="empty">
            <t>Stage 3 - jCard deprecation</t>
            <t>This stage corresponds to the provisioning of JSCard as default contact card but the RDAP server is able to alternatively return jCard if the client sets the query parameter "jcard" to 1/true/yes. The rdapConformance array contains the "jscard_level_0" tag unless jCard is requested. The "jscard" query parameter is ignored.</t>
            <t>The RDAP server is recommended to return a notice titled "jCard deprecation end". Such a notice should include a description reporting the jCard deprecation end time and two links: 
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>"deprecation": a link to a URI-identified resource documenting the jCard deprecation;</t>
              <t>"alternate": if jCard is not requested, a link to the jCard version of the same resource as identified by the current query string plus the parameter "jcard" set to 1/true/yes (<xref target="stage3-example1" />); otherwise, a link to the JSCard version of the same resource as identified by the current query string without the parameter "jcard" (<xref target="stage3-example2" />).</t>
            </list></t>
          </list></t>
          <figure anchor="stage3-example1" title="jCard deprecation - jCard not requested"><artwork xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA["notices": [
  {
    "title": "jCard deprecation end",
    "description": ["2020-12-31T23:59:59Z"],
    "links": [
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX",
        "rel": "deprecation",
        "type": "text/html",
        "href": "http://www.example.com/jcard_deprecation.html"
      },
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX",
        "rel": "alternate",
        "type": "application/rdap+json",
        "href": " http://example.net/entity/XXXX?jcard=1"
      }
    ]
  }
]
]]></artwork></figure>
          <figure anchor="stage3-example2" title="jCard deprecation - jCard requested"><artwork xml:space="preserve">
<![CDATA["notices": [
  {
    "title": "jCard deprecation end",
    "description": ["2020-12-31T23:59:59Z"],
    "links": [
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX?jcard=1",
        "rel": "deprecation",
        "type": "text/html",
        "href": "http://www.example.com/jcard_deprecation.html"
      },
      {
        "value": "http://example.net/entity/XXXX?jcard=1",
        "rel": "alternate",
        "type": "application/rdap+json",
        "href": " http://example.net/entity/XXXX"
      }
    ]
  }
]
]]></artwork></figure>
          <t>
            <list style="empty">
              <t>Stage 4 - jCard deprecated</t>
              <t>This stage corresponds to providing JSCard as default contact card. The RDAP server is not able to provide an alternate contact card. The rdapConformance array always contains "jscard_level_0" tag. The RDAP server doesn't include any notice about the jCard deprecation process. Both "jscard" and "jcard" query parameters are ignored.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="jcard-deprecation-procedure-length" title="Length">
          <t>The length of both jCard sunset and jCard deprecation periods are not fixed by this specification. Best practices in REST API deprecation suggest that, depending on the deprecated API's reach, user base and service offering, a convenient time could be anywhere between 3 - 8 months. Anyway, RDAP providers are recommended to monitor the server log to figure out whether declared times need to be changed to meet client requirements.</t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="jcard-deprecation-procedure-goals" title="Goals">
          <t>The procedure described in this document achieves the following goals:</t>
          <t>
            <list style="symbols">
              <t>only one contact representation would be included in the response;</t>
              <t>the response would always be compliant to RFC7483;</t>
              <t>clients would be informed about the transition timeline;</t>
              <t>the backward compatibility would be guaranteed throughout the transition;</t>
              <t>servers and clients could execute their transitions independently.</t>
            </list>
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="impl-status" title="Implementation Status">
      <t>NOTE: Please remove this section and the reference to RFC 7942 prior to publication as an RFC.</t>
      
      <t>This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft, and is based on a proposal described in RFC 7942 <xref target="RFC7942"/>. The description of implementations in this section is intended to assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing drafts to RFCs. Please note that the listing of any individual implementation here does not imply endorsement by the IETF. Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here that was supplied by IETF contributors. This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be, a catalog of available implementations or their features. Readers are advised to note that other implementations may exist.</t>
      
      <t>According to RFC 7942, &quot;this will allow reviewers and working groups to assign due consideration to documents that have the benefit of running code, which may serve as evidence of valuable experimentation and feedback that have made the implemented protocols more mature. It is up to the individual working groups to use this information as they see fit&quot;.</t>
      
      <section anchor="iit-cnr-registro-it" title="IIT-CNR/Registro.it">
        <t><list style="none">
    	  <t>Responsible Organization: Institute of Informatics and Telematics of National Research Council (IIT-CNR)/Registro.it</t>
    	  <t>Location: https://rdap.pubtest.nic.it/</t>
    	  <t>Description: This implementation includes support for RDAP queries using data from the public test environment of .it ccTLD.</t>
    	  <t>Level of Maturity: This is a &quot;proof of concept&quot; research implementation.</t>
    	  <t>Coverage: This implementation includes all of the features described in this specification.</t>
    	  <t>Contact Information: Mario Loffredo, mario.loffredo@iit.cnr.it</t>
    	</list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

   <section anchor="IANA-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>IANA is requested to register the following values in the RDAP Extensions Registry:</t>

     <t><list style="none">
       <t>Extension identifier: jscard</t>
       <t>Registry operator: Any</t>
       <t>Published specification: This document.</t>
       <t>Contact: IESG &lt;iesg@ietf.org&gt;</t>
       <t>Intended usage: This extension represents a contact card provided in an RDAP response according to the JSContact specification (<xref target="draft-ietf-jmap-jscontact"/>) .</t>
     </list></t>

   </section>

   <section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
  	<t>Unlike jCard, the formatted name as well as any other personally identifiable information is not required in JSCard. The only mandatory property, namely &quot;uid&quot; is usually an opaque string. Therefore, redacted properties can be merely excluded without using placeholder values.</t>
   </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC3339;
      &RFC6350;
      &RFC7095;
      &RFC7482;
      &RFC7483;
      &RFC7942;
      &RFC8288;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="draft-ietf-jmap-jscontact" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-jmap-jscontact/">
        <front><title>JSContact: A JSON representation of contact data</title>
          <author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek" />
          <author initials="M." surname="Loffredo" fullname="Mario Loffredo" />
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="draft-loffredo-jmap-jscontact-vcard" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-loffredo-jmap-jscontact-vcard/">
        <front><title>JSContact: Converting from and to vCard</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Loffredo" fullname="Mario Loffredo" />
          <author initials="R." surname="Stepanek" fullname="Robert Stepanek" />
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="draft-dalal-deprecation-header" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-dalal-deprecation-header/">
        <front><title>The Deprecation HTTP Header Field</title>
          <author initials="S." surname="Dalal" fullname="Sanjay Dalal" />
          <author initials="E." surname="Wilde" fullname="Erik Wilde" />
          <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor='RDAP-PILOT-WG' target='https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/rdap-pilot-report-25apr19-en.pdf'>
        <front>
          <title>RDAP Pilot Report</title>
          <author>
            <organization>ICANN RDAP Pilot WG</organization>
          </author>
          <date year='2019' month='April' />		
        </front>
      </reference>
    </references>

    <section title="Change Log">

      <section title="Change from 00 to 01">
        <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>Changed category from &quot;Best Current Practice&quot; to &quot;Standards Track&quot;</t>
          <t>Changed title of the &quot;Migration from JCard to JSCard&quot; section to &quot;Transition Considerations&quot;</t>
          <t>Added the &quot;RDAP Conformance&quot; section</t>
          <t>Updated the &quot;IANA Considerations&quot; section</t>
          <t>Updated the &quot;Security Considerations&quot; section</t>
          <t>Replaced the example of the &quot;Using JSCard objects in RDAP Responses&quot; section with one taken from RFC7483</t>
          <t>Changed the names of the transition stages 1 and 2</t>
          <t>Corrected <xref target="stage2-example1"/>, <xref target="stage3-example1"/>, <xref target="stage3-example2"/></t>
         </list></t>
      </section>

    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
